When we started this lesson, we create our models by inspection, however,
我们开始这节课时 经过检验创建了模型
most of the time we want to train using the data itself.
然而大多数时候 我们想让训练数据本身
When using HMMs for gesture recognition, I like to have at least 12 examples for
使用隐马尔可夫模型进行手势识别 我想识别至少每个手势包含 12 个例子
each gesture I'm trying to recognize, five examples at a minimum.
最少的有 5 个例子
&gt;&gt; For illustration purposes let's just use three examples of data for
— 为了说明目的 我们使用手势 I 数据的
gesture I.
3 个例子
Even though it's not the best feature we are going to continue using delta Y for
即使这不是最好的特征 我们还是使用 Δy
training, the first example is the longest,it has 16 data points.
进行训练 第一个例子最长 包括 16 个数据点
&gt;&gt; And I see the next one is really short was only five data points.
— 我看到接下来的例子很短 只包括 5 个数据点
The last one has 14 timeframes.
最后一个包括 14 个时间帧
Let's use a three state left to right topology again for HMM.
我们再次使用从左向右拓扑图的三个状态 表示隐马尔可夫模型
For each of this examples,
在这些例子中
how are we going to figure out which data goes with which state?
我们怎样分辨哪个数据与哪个状态匹配呢？
&gt;&gt; Let's assume all three states have about an equal number of frames.
— 我们假设三个状态帧数相同
I've divided the examples roughly in the thirds and
我大体把这些例子各分成三份
drawn a boundary between each third.
在三分之一的地方画上分界线
&gt;&gt; On average our example 12x frames long.
— 一般来说我们这个例子长度是 12 帧
So that means about 4 data points per status, for example.
所以这表明每个状态包括 4 个数据点
&gt;&gt; Yup,
— 没错
which means a transition probability out of this stage is going to be 1/4.
这表明这个状态的转移概率是 1/4
&gt;&gt; And since the transitions probability have to sum to one for each state.
— 既然各状态的转移概率总和为 1
The self transitions are 3/4.
自转换为 3/4
&gt;&gt; Now that we've fixed the transition probabilities,
— 既然已经调整了转移概率
let's calculate the output probabilities.
我们要计算输出概率
&gt;&gt; For simplicity, let's use a single Gaussian again.
— 为了简化 我们再次使用高斯分布
For the first state, we assign the 1 3 7 9 7 from the first example and
在第一个状态中 我们从第一个样本中得到 1 3 7 9 7
the 2 and 10 from the second example and the 1 3 7 8 7 to this first state.
第二个样本中是 2 和 10 在这个样本中是 1 3 7 8 7
The average of that is approximately 5.4.
这些数的平均数约为 5.4
The standard deviation is, hold on there,
标准差是 稍等一下
let me get out my copy of Octave, about 3.1.
我通过 Octave 语言计算得到约 3.1
Let me draw this under the first state as its output probability.
我们在第一个状态下面这样绘制 作为输出概率
&gt;&gt; Since you're being handy, can you do the other states too?
— 既然你已经掌握了 可以完成其他状态吗？
We can calculate the mean value of the second state.
我们计算第二个状态的平均值
It's around negative 0.6 with a standard deviation of 3.1.
约为 -0.6 标准差是 3.1
The last state has a mean of minus 5, standard deviation of about 2.6.
最后一个状态平均值是 -5 标准差是 2.6
&gt;&gt; Let's try those out probabilities as well.
— 我们也来计算出这些概率
&gt;&gt; Now we're going to iterate in the process very similar to expectation
— 现在我们要迭代这个过程
maximization.
与期望最大化非常相似
&gt;&gt; So basically we reset the transition probabilities and
— 一般说来我们重置转移概率
calculated the output probabilities based on the assumption that
根据对正确转移概率的假设
the transition probabilities are correct.
计算输出概率
Then we're going to assume that the output probabilities are correct and
然后我们要假设输出概率是正确的
go back and adjust the transition probabilities and so
然后回去调整转移概率
on until we converge.
如此往复 直到我们收敛到一点
&gt;&gt; So basically our next step is to see if moving these boundaries on these
— 我们下一步是观察如果移动状态之间的分界线
examples between the states will lead to a better explanation of the data.
会不会更好地解释数据
Basically, we are looking to see if we get Gaussian of less variance.
一般来说 我们要观察是否得到更小方差的高斯分布
&gt;&gt; Well,
— 好
that could be interesting, let's look at the first boundary in the first example.
很有趣 我们首先看第一个例子的第一个分界线
Cleary the 5 is closer to the mean of 5.4 so
显然 5 更加接近平均值 5.4
the boundary should move to the right.
分界线应该向右移动
&gt;&gt; But the two might be better than a second state.
— 不过 2 最好放在第二个状态中
&gt;&gt; How do you display that?
— 如何体现出来呢？
&gt;&gt; Well two is 3.4 the mean of the first state.
— 2 到第一个状态均值 3.4
Which is 3.4 over 3.1 standard deviations away.
即 3.4 除以 3.1 标准差的距离较远
In other words two is a little more than one standard deviation
换句话说 2 到第一个状态标准差的距离
away from the first state.
超过 1
&gt;&gt; Okay.
— 好
&gt;&gt; But the mean for the second state is -0.6 which make the two
— 不过第二个状态的均值是 -0.6
only 2.6 units away from the mean of the second state.
2 到第二个状态均值的距离只有 2.6
Or 2.6 over 3.1 standard deviations away.
或者 2.6 除以 3.1 标准差的距离
&gt;&gt; Which is less than one standard deviation away.
— 与标准差的距离小于 1
So two should stay in the second state.
所以 2 应该放在第二个状态中
&gt;&gt; For now.
— 目前为止
&gt;&gt; What do you mean, for now?
— 你指的是什么呢？
&gt;&gt; By the time we finish this iteration, the mean and standard deviations for
— 目前为止我们完成这个迭代 这个状态的均值和标准差
the states will change and
会发生变化
two might move in the first state in the next round.
2 会在下一轮移动到第一个状态中
&gt;&gt; Okay, but how many of the boundaries change in this iteration?
— 好 但是这次迭代多少个分界线会发生变化呢？
&gt;&gt; Let's look.
— 我们来看一下
I don't think the -1 is going to move from the second stage.
我认为 -1 不能移动到第二个状态
&gt;&gt; But in the second example this -7 is much closer to the mean of third stage -5.
— 但是第二个例子中 -7 更加靠近第三个状态的均值 -5
&gt;&gt; Yup, let's move the boundary.
— 没错 我们要移动分界线
&gt;&gt; Shouldn't we update the mean in variance.
— 我们是不是应该更新方差中的均值呢？
&gt;&gt; Its better to face looking at rest of the boundaries first.
— 最好先观察剩余分界线
Last example looks like we have a lot of things we can move.
最后一个例子中 看起来我们要移动许多东西
&gt;&gt; Right, the three should probably move from the second state to the first.
— 没错 3 应该从第二个状态移动到第一个
&gt;&gt; And certainly the minus five should go from the second to the third.
— 显然 -5 应该从第二个状态移动到第三个
&gt;&gt; How about the negative three in the second state.
— 第二个状态中的 -3 呢？
I have to calculate that one out quick.
我要快速计算出来这个
It's 2.4/3.1 standard deviations from the second state.
这是第二个状态的标准差 2.4/3.1
And two over 2.6 standard deviations from the mean of the third state.
2/2.6 第三个状态均值的标准差
It is slightly closer to the mean of the third state, though not by much.
略微接近第三个状态的均值 虽然没有非常接近
&gt;&gt; Great, let's update the boundaries again.
— 好 我们再次更新分界线
&gt;&gt; Wow, that's going to cause a big change in our numbers.
— 哇塞 这会让我们的数字发生很大变化
&gt;&gt; Yep, let's recalculate everything.
— 没错 我们已经重新计算了一切
&gt;&gt; On average, we now have one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight,
— 一般说来我们现在有 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8
nine, ten, 11, 12, 13, 14.
9 10 11 12 13 14
14 over three time frames we expect in the first date.
第一个状态中 3 个时间帧中总共 14 个数字
So our transition probability here is going to be one over 4.7.
所以这里我们的转移概率是 1 除以 4.7
Or approximately 0.21 making the self-loop 0.79.
约为 0.21 自循环为 0.79
&gt;&gt; The second state has 7 over 3 time frames on average.
— 第二个状态的 3 个时间帧有 7 个数字
Transition probably there will be .43 and .57.
转换概率分别为 0.43 和 0.57
&gt;&gt; And the last state has 14 over 3 time frames on average or
— 最后一个状态的 3 个时间帧有 14 个数字
approximate 0.21 transition probability here and 0.79 probability here.
转换概率也是 0.21 这里概率为 0.79
&gt;&gt; Okay, so now we need to update the output probability numbers.
— 好 我们现在需要更新输出概率的数字
&gt;&gt; I was afraid you are going to say that.
— 我担心你要这么说
Okay, clinging at octave again, I get a mean of 5.2 and
好 再次依靠 Octava 我得到第一个状态输出概率均值 5.2
a standard deviation of 3.0 for the output probability for the first state.
标准差 3.0
&gt;&gt; Come on, you're the one with the computer.
— 来吧 你是拥有计算机的人
What's the rest?
其他的呢？
&gt;&gt; Fine, state two is easy.
— 状态 2 比较简单
It has a mean of 0 and a standard deviation of 1.
均值是 0 标准差是 1
&gt;&gt; Do you do that on purpose?
— 你那样做是故意的吗？
&gt;&gt; What?
— 什么？
&gt;&gt; Make the example so the numbers would come out nice?
— 利用这个例子 然后得到这样好的数字？
&gt;&gt; I wish I was that smart.
— 我希望是那么聪明
&gt;&gt; I'm so disillusioned.
— 我有点不抱幻想了
Okay, what are the values for state three?
那么状态 3 的值是多少？
&gt;&gt; State three's mean is -5 and standard deviation about 2.5.
— 状态 3 的均值是 -5 标准差是 2.5
&gt;&gt; Great, now we can do our next iteration.
— 很棒 现在我们要进行下一轮迭代了
&gt;&gt; You mean, we gotta do it again?
— 你是说我们还要重复一次？
&gt;&gt; Don't be a cry baby, it's almost done.
— 不要担心 我们已经完成了
&gt;&gt; Okay, well, as I predicted, this 2 is now closer to the first state
— 正如我预测的那样 在这次对第二个状态迭代过程中
on this iteration in the second state &gt;&gt; Well, I guess you win that one.
2 更加接近第一个状态 — 好 我想你赢了一次
It's just a little over one standard deviation from the mean of the first
它只是略微高于第一个状态均值的
state.
标准差
And two standard deviations from the mean of the second state.
第二个状态均值的两个标准差
&gt;&gt; But the -1 still stays in the second state.
— 不过 -1 还是放在第二个状态中
&gt;&gt; Yup, in both places.
— 没错 两处都是这样
&gt;&gt; So let's calculate again.
— 那我们重新计算一次
&gt;&gt; Now state one's mean goes to five.
— 现在状态 1 均值是 5
State two's mean goes to slightly negative.
状态 2 均值是负数
And state three's mean stays the same.
状态 3 均值保持不变
&gt;&gt; I think we've converged.
— 我认为我们收敛到一点
Let me take a look.
我来看一下
Yeah, in the next iteration none of the boundaries are going to move nor
在下一次迭代中没有移动分界线
are the ALPA probability is going to change.
也没有 α 发生变化
&gt;&gt; Does that mean we've successfully trained HMM for I?
— 是不是说我们成功训练了 I 的隐马尔可夫模型
&gt;&gt; Not yet.
— 并没有
Technically speaking, what we've done is use Viterbi
从技术角度来说 我们使用 Viterbi 对齐
alignment to initialize the values for each state of our HMM.
对隐马尔可夫模型每个状态的值进行了初始化
In other words, for each time frame in each of our
换句话说 对于所有例子中的每个时间帧
examples we've assigned a state for that time frame and
我们已经调整了时间帧的状态
calculated the resulting averages of all values assigned to each state.
并且计算了每个状态所有值的平均结果
&gt;&gt; Along with the average amount of time we expect to stay in each state.
— 还有我们希望停留在每个状态中的平均次数
&gt;&gt; Correct.
— 没错